The Life Of Muhammadﷺ, The Madinan Period, Volume 1
By Imam Anwar Al_Awlaki,
اَعُوْذُ بِاللهِ مِنَّ الشِّيْطَانِ الرَّجِيْمِ۝بِسْمِ اللهِ الرَّحْمَانِ الرَّحِيْمَ۝
اَلْحَمْدُ لله ، وَالصَّلَاةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلى سَيِّدِنَا محمد وَعَلَى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ
رَبِّ اشْرَحْ لِي صَدْرِي۝وَيَسِّرْ لِي أَمْرِي۝وَاحْلُلْ عُقْدَةً مِنْ لِسَانِي۝يَفْقَهُوا قَوْلِي۝
السلام عليكم ورحمة الله وبركاته
To all the listeners.
Before we start with the Battle of Uhud(اُحَدْ)
a few scattered Ghazawaat(غزوات) and Saraya(سراية) that occurred after Badr(بدر) and before Uhud(اُحَدْ).
One of them is Ghazwat Ma-Qadar(غزوة ما قدر)
and Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله), seven days after the Battle of Badr(بدر).
The Muslims were already on the road.
They went to attack this was a preemptive attack on Bannu Sulaim(بنوسليم).
Bannu Sulaim(بنوسليم), a tribe Rasool Allah ﷺ caught word
that they were gathering to attack Madina, so Rasool Allah ﷺ attacked them first.
This was something that repeats throughout the Ghazawat(غزوات) of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
he hears that people are plotting to attack Madina,
so he starts first and takes the initiative and takes advantage of the surprise attack.
And they surprised Bannu Sulaim(بنوسليم),
so Bannu Sulaim(بنوسليم) fled the scene and they left behind 500 camels
which ended up being a good booty for the Muslims, each soldier ended up getting about two camels
and they went back to Madina.
There was another Ghazwa(غزوة) called Ghazwat As-Suwaik(غزوةإلسويق).
Abu Sufiyan(ابوسفيان), trying to wash away the shame of Badr(بدر), goes to Bannu Nadhir(بنو نضير),
the Jewish tribe of Bannu Nadhir(بنو نضير).
They stay as guests of Salam Bin Mashkam(سلام بن مشكم), the head of Bannu Nadhir(بنو نضير).
And they get some valuable information from him, some insider information.
And they attack the outskirts of Madina, they find over there two Muslims, they killed them,
they destroy the area just took some stuff with him and left.
So, it wasn't much of revenge for Badr(بدر).
Rasool Allah ﷺ heard about it and he immediately pursued them with 200 soldiers.
And Abu Sufiyan(ابوسفيان) had 200 soldiers with him too
but he was running away.
And they were so terrified.
They were throwing their food stuff,
this is particular kind of food that they will take with them.
It's kind of food that doesn't spoil, it's called Suwaik(سويق).
Apparently it's some grains and it's mixed with butter or honey
and they would carry it with them and since its expiration date is very late,
it's pretty good food for fighters.
So, they were throwing away this food to lighten the load and they ran away.
So no fighting occurred in Ghazwat As-Suwaik(غزوة إلسويق).
In another Ghazwa(غزوة), Ghazwat Ghimr(غزوة الغمر) four Hundred and fifty(450) Muslims.
And this was against a tribe in Najd(نجد).
And Rasool Allah ﷺ attack them because he heard that they were planning to attack him.
So, he goes to meet them in their own territory.
On the way he arrests one of their men called Jabbar Bin Thalaba(جبار بن ثالبه), who becomes Muslim.
And then when they reached to the enemy's land,
it was rainy, so the cloths of Rasool Allah ﷺ got wet,
so Rasool Allah ﷺ took off his armor and hanged it on a tree,
so that his clothes could dry and then he laid down under a tree.
So, Ja'soor(جعثور), the head of the
enemy's army sneaked in,
and he stood right above Rasool Allah ﷺ with his sword in hand.
And while Rasool Allah ﷺ was sleeping, he woke him up and said,
O Muhammad(محمد)
مَنْ يَمْنَعُكَ مِنِّيْ الْآنْ
Who can save you from me now?
Rasool Allah ﷺ with all confidence, said: Allah.
Suddenly Ja'soor(جعثور) falls back and his sword fell.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ picks up the sword and stands on top of Ja'soor(جعثور) and says;
Ya Ja'soor(يا جعثور)! Who can protect you from me now?
So, he pleads to Rasool Allah ﷺ to spare him, his life.
And he became Muslim.
He goes back to his people and his people blame him, they said,
what's your problem, what's happened to you?
He said; A tall man stood in front of me and pushed me in my chest.
And that was Jibreel عليه السّلام.
So, Ja'soor(جعثور), who wanted to kill Rasool Allah ﷺ becomes Muslim.
He goes back gives his people Da'wah(دعوة) many of them become Muslim,
a miracle, of the miracles of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
But this was a one month long journey,
I mean they were absent for an entire month.
And then there is a Sariyya(سرية), Zaid Bin Harissa(زيد بن حارثه).
So, this is a Sariyya(سرية), Rasool Allah ﷺ didn't go with them, to Kiradah(كردة).
The people of Quraish(قريش), were now suffering economically, because of the continuous raids.
The Muslims were putting some serious pressure on Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) by raiding their caravans.
I mean, now the route from Makkah to Syria was jeopardized.
The Muslims are all over the place,
either their armies or tribes loyal to them,
because Rasool Allah ﷺ was sending out these Sarayya(سراية),
to engage with the tribes surrounding Madina to invite them to Islam
or to at least make some alliances with them, to guarantee that they would stand on the Muslim side.
So, now Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), her line to Syria was threatened.
So, they were consulting with some guides and they told them that
well, if the roots of Hijaz(حجاز) are not safe. Why don't we go through Najd(نجد).?
So, they're going to take this long turn through Najd(نجد), getting close to Iraq(عراق),
and then from there, they're going to enter into Syria
which obviously costs more and takes longer but they had to do, what they had to do.
So, they sent this caravan to go through Najd(نجد) and from Iraq and then into Syria.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ sends out Sariyya(سرية) led by Zaid Bin Harissa(زيد بن حارثه) and a 100 Muslims to raid it.
This just drove them crazy.
And it was a successful attack.
The guards of the caravan ran away.
And the Muslims took over the caravan says it had so much silver in it.
Now these skirmishes or small battles and Ghazawaat(غزوات) served few objectives of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
First of all there were hands on military training
Number two, and this issue of military training is Ibadah(عبادة) in itself.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
وَأَعِدُّوا لَهُمْ مَا اسْتَطَعْتُمْ مِنْ قُوَّةٍ
Prepare whatever strength you can.
So, any training that could help the Muslim in Jihad(جهاد) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله) is Ibadah(عبادة).
It's just like praying" fasting, paying Zakah(زكواة), it's Ibadah(عبادة).
And if Jihad(جهاد) is Fardh(فرض) then the preparation becomes Fardh(فرض) too.
So, they were worshiping Allahعَزّوجَلّ through this training.
It was hands on military training,
it wasn't in a military school or it was in the field, actual training.
Number two, it's Tarbiyyah(تربية).
Because the Sahabah(صحابه) would spend long time with Rasool Allah ﷺ.
So, for example, in the Ghazwa(غزوة) that we just talked about, they were absent for an entire month.
So, they were spending this time with Rasool Allah ﷺ,
traveling with him, eating with him, walking with him,
and you get exposed to some aspects of a person's personality in travel,
that you might not be exposed to, if a person is residing in their home,
because the mixing and mingling, when you are traveling with somebody is more.
So, the Sahabah(صحابه) get to see the personality of Rasool Allah ﷺ in front of their eyes
and this is how they learned the Sunnah(سنة) of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
So, they would learn about his Ibadah(عبادة)
and they would also, the third benefit of these Ghazawaat(غزوات) Is.
It teaches the Muslim how to be a member of a group of a Jama'a(جماعة).
Because there is Samman Ta'ah (سمعا طاعة) there is obedience, there is discipline, there is sacrifice,
because you know, you are part of a group, you're not just an individual doing your own thing.
So, these are habits that they get to learn by traveling for such long extended periods, with Rasool Allah ﷺ,
so it was also a Tarbiyyah(تربية) for them, and how to be part of the Ummah(أمة)
because Islam is not individualistic religion, it's a collective religion,
a lot of the Ibadaat(عبادات) in Islam are done collectively,
Salah(صلاة) is done collectively,
Hajj(حج) is done collectively, Umrah(عمره) is done collectively,
Jihad(جهاد) most of the time is done collectively.
So, all of these Ibadaat(عبادات), that they get to learn from Rasool Allah ﷺ in the field.
We move on to the Battle of Uhud(اُحَدْ),
what were the reasons for the Battle of Uhud(اُحَدْ)?
There were religious reasons, economical reasons, political reasons and social reasons.
The religious reason,
the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) wanted to stop the advance of Islam.
They wanted to stand between the people and becoming Muslim.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
إِنَّ الَّذِينَ كَفَرُوا يُنْفِقُونَ أَمْوَالَهُمْ لِيَصُدُّوا عَنْ سَبِيلِ اللَّهِ ۚ
فَسَيُنْفِقُونَهَا ثُمَّ تَكُونُ عَلَيْهِمْ حَسْرَةً ثُمَّ يُغْلَبُونَ ۗ
وَالَّذِينَ كَفَرُوا إِلَىٰ جَهَنَّمَ يُحْشَرُونَ۝
Indeed, those who disbelieve spend their wealth to avert people from the way of Allah.
So they will spend it,
then it will be for them a source of regret,
then they will be overcome.
And those who have disbelieved on to hell they will be gathered.
So, it says here that they're spending their wealth to avert people from the way of Allah.
At-Tabri(ألطبري) says;
يَصْرِفُوْنَ اَمْوَالَهُمْ وَيُنْفِقُوْنَهَا لْيَمْنَعُ النَّاسَ مِنْ دُخُوْلِ الْاِسْلَامْ
They're spending their money to prevent people from becoming Muslim.
And Ash-Shoukani(ألشوكاني) says about this Ayah(آية),
وَالْمَعْنَى اَنَّ غَرَضَ هَا اُوْلآءِ الْكُفَّارْ فِيْ اَنْفَاقِ اَمْوَالِهِمْ هُوَّ صَدُّ عَنْ سَبِيْلِ الله بِمُحَارَبَةِ رَسُول الله وَجَمْعِ الْجُيُوْشِ لِذَالِكْ
The meaning, is that the objective of these Kuffar(كفار) in spending their money,
is to stand between the people and becoming Muslim, by fighting Rasool Allah ﷺ
and mobilizing armies, for that purpose.
And history is repeating itself,
look at how much money, the enemies of Allahعَزّوجَلّ are spending to fight Islam
billions of dollars are spent for that
to kill the Ouleaa(أوليآء) of Allahعَزّوجَلّ, to around them up, to capture them
and to tarnish the reputation of Islam,
lots of money is spent for that purpose.
So, the kuffar(كفار) of today are not very different from the kuffar(كفار) of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
The social reason,
Quraish(قريش) wanted to wash away the shame of Badr(بدر).
That was a serious dent in the reputation and they wanted to make up for that.
The economical reason,
we talked about how those raids were putting serious pressure on the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ),
who were accustomed to having all the Arabs respect them, and opened the way for them, to both Yemen and Syria.
But now things are different
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
لِإِيلَافِ قُرَيْشٍ۝
إِيلَافِهِمْ رِحْلَةَ الشِّتَاءِ وَالصَّيْفِ ۝
فَلْيَعْبُدُوا رَبَّ هَٰذَا الْبَيْتِ ۝
الَّذِي أَطْعَمَهُمْ مِنْ جُوعٍ وَآمَنَهُمْ مِنْ خَوْفٍ۝
For the accustomed security of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), they were accustomed to security.
Their accustomed security, in the caravan of winter and summer.
The caravan of winter was to Yemen and the caravan of summer was to Syria.
Let them worship, the Lord of this house, who has fed them,
saving them from hunger and made them safe,
saving them from fear,
but because they refused to worship Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
Now that accustomed security was gone.
Now only one leg of their journey was affected, and that is from Makkah to Syria.
Because they had two Journeys, one was from Makkah to Yemen and Abyssinia
the second one was from Makkah to Syria.
The journey of Syria was done in summer
and the journey to Yemen and Abyssinia was in winter.
However, cutting the route to Syria affects also the route to Yemen,
Why?
Because the business of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) was based on buying products from Yemen
and selling them in Syria and vice versa.
So, since now they are having difficulty going to Syria,
that will also affect their business in Yemen because they end up selling those products of Syria in Yemen.
So, Safwaan Ibn Ummayyah(صفوان ابن امية) says;
Muhammad(محمد) and his companions have ruined our trade,
while we do not know, what measures to take against them, we are at lost,
they are constantly threatening the coastal area,
while its inhabitants are either at peace or alliance with him.
Where shall we live?
And where should we stay?
If we stay here in our hometown,
we will be forced to eat from our capital, which will soon be consumed
we depend for our lives on trade with Syria in the summer
and with Yemen and Abyssinia in winter.
So, Muhammadﷺ was squeezing Makkah tight,
they were feeling suffocated.
And this shows you the strategy of Rasool Allah ﷺ
of not only afflicting physical harm at Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), in actual warfare, battles on the battle ground,
but also giving attention to the economical war against Quraish(قُرَيْشْ),
which was an important part of the strategy of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
And then you have the political reason, the status of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) was shaken.
You know, this outstanding victory of the Muslims,
seriously weakened the reputation of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) in Arabia,
which was seen as the noble most respected tribe.
You don't fight against Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), you respect them.
So, now all of this was changing the status quo was not the status quo anymore.
So, they wanted to regain their reputation again.
So, there was a political reason.
So, Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) assembles an army 3000 strong
and they financed that army from the caravan, which Abu Sufiyan(ابوسفيان) saved.
The one that was the cause for the Battle of Badr(بدر).
You remembered that caravan.
This caravan its entire wealth, everything in that Caravan was used to finance the Battle of Uhud(اُحَدْ).
Rasool Allah ﷺ is constantly receiving information, he has spies all over.
Al-Abbas Bin Abdul Muttalib(العباس بن عبدالمطلب) now is working for Rasool Allah ﷺ in Makkah.
So, he sends a message to Rasool Allah ﷺ, which was carried swiftly in three days,
which is impressive for the modes of transportation in those days
to cut the distance between Makkah and Madina in three days. That's pretty good, it's fast.
So, a letter is conveyed to Rasool Allah ﷺ telling him the details,
an army of 3000.
They have 700 coat males,
they have such and such, number of camels.
So, he was being elaborate in the details.
So, this is the first news that reaches Rasool Allah ﷺ of the plans of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
And the source of this information was Al-Abbas Bin Abdul Muttalib رضي الله عنه.
When the news was delivered to Rasool Allah ﷺ,
he told Ubaye Bin Ka'ab(أبيئ بن كعب), who read the letter, keep this secret.
Don't tell anybody about it.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ sends Al-Mundhir(ألمنذر), to go and blend in within the army and get him information.
So, he comes back with the same details which were narrated by Al-Abbas(العباس).
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ is collaborating the information from more than one source.
And then he sends out Anas(انس) and Muanus(مؤنس)
same thing, to go inside the army of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) and bring in news
and they come back and same thing.
Now Rasool Allah ﷺ then goes to one of the chiefs of Al-Ansaar(الأنْصَار), Saad Ibn Rabiyyah(سعد إبن ربيعة).
He visits him at his house.
And he tells him that Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) is attacking us.
He gives him some of the details.
And he gets his opinion.
And he then before he leaves, he tells him keep this secret,
keep this information secret, it classified.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ leaves, the wife of Saad Ibn Rabiyyah(سعد إبن ربيعة) comes to him and says;
What did Rasool Allah ﷺ tell you?
He tells her; it's none of your business.
She said, Well, Rasool Allah ﷺ told you this and that because I heard him,
Saad Ibn Rabiyyah(سعد إبن ربيعة) said:
إِنَّا لِلّهِ وَإِنَّا إِلَيْهِ رَاجِعونَ
This is what you say when a disaster happens.
And then he goes to Rasool Allah ﷺ and tells him,
My wife knows about it.
And I came to tell you that if, just in case the information gets out,
I don't want you to think that I'm the one who leaked it.
Rasool Allah ﷺ told him
خَلِّيْ عَنْهَا
Leave her alone.
Now we learned from this that a secret is a secret.
You don't have to tell it, to anyone.
Saad Ibn Rabiyyah(سعد إبن ربيعة) refused to tell it to his own wife.
And he made it very clear, I'm not going to tell you, it's none of your business.
And in such issues relating to the security of the Muslims and military operations.
Rasool Allah ﷺ would function with the Sahabah(صحابه) on a need to know basis.
And somebody who doesn't have to know this information doesn't have to know it.
So, Saad Ibn Rabiyyah(سعد إبن ربيعة) just because, this is his wife,
didn't go and tell her; well Rasool Allah ﷺ told me this and that,
he wasn't trying to impress his wife that Rasool Allah ﷺ came to me and told me about it.
He wasn't being trusting of anyone to give them this information.
And I'm stressing on this point, because many times,
we just assume that because we trust a particular person, we can tell them everything.
If this information is a trust,
it's an Amana(امانة), with you, then you have to treat it as such. It's an Amana(امانة)..
And if somebody tells you the secret and you go and talk about it, then you have, you're being dishonest.
خَيَانَة الْاَمَانَهْ
not keeping the trust.
Also, I want to add that a husband is inclined to tell his wife about everything, that's not right.
Some issues need to be kept away from the closest of your relatives,
parents, wife, children, because again, this is an Amana(امانة).
Now, I hope that my sisters won't be offended by what I've just said.
But emotions sometimes can affect a person male or female.
However, the makeup of females is that they are more emotional than men.
This is not the case in every situation.
We're talking about the majority.
And sisters, the wife would be quite upset that her husband is keeping away information from her sometimes.
But you need to understand the context of the situation
that it was something that is regarding the security of the nation
of the Muslim Ummah(امة).
And I hope that, also the brothers wouldn't take these words and abuse them
and try to keep away information that the wife needs to know.
So, I hope that this is not taken out of context.
Rasool Allah ﷺ holds a Shura(شورى), meeting with the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم, on what to do.
So now it's about time to tell the Muslims about what's happening.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ gathers them and asks them,
what do they think?
There were two opinions.
One, we should fight within Madina
and use it as a fortress and fight in the streets.
And therefore the women and children would be able to participate in the fighting
by fighting from the roofs by throwing rocks at the enemy.
And this was the opinion of Rasool Allah ﷺ
and also this was the opinion of Abdullah Bin Obaeye(عبدالله بن ابي), for different reasons.
Rasool Allah ﷺ from a strategic point of view, adopted this opinion.
But Abdullah Bin Obaeye(عبدالله بن ابي) because he was too afraid to go out and fight.
While the majority opinion was to go out and meet the enemy in open field
and their reasoning is that it is shameful for us to hide inside Madina
and have them come and attack us, in our own home.
But we would go out and meet them and not allow them to even come close to Madina
and this was the opinion of, the ones who did not attend Badr(بدر).
They felt that they missed a lot by not being at Badr(بدر),
so they were so eager to meet the enemy
and they were afraid that if they stay in Madina the enemy wouldn't dare to come in
and they didn't want to miss the Fighting.
And this group, the group who adopted this opinion
put some pressure on Rasool Allah ﷺ until, he agreed to adopt their opinion.
So, he stood up and left the meeting and went inside his house to put on his armor.
They felt that they have pressured Rasool Allah ﷺ, so they go to Hamza(حمزه) and say,
go and talk to Rasool Allah ﷺ, we felt that we've pressured him
and we willing to go with what he thinks is, the better opinion.
So, Hamza(حمزه) goes to Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Rasool Allah ﷺ comes out and says;
مَا يَنْبَغِيْ لِنَبِيٍّ اَنْ يَنْزَعْ لَأمة الْحَرْبِ اِذَا وَضَعَهَا حَتَّى يَحْكُمُ الله بَيْنَه’ وَبَيْنَ عَدُّوَّ اَوْ كَمَا قَالَ صَلَّى الله عليه وسلم
Rasool Allah ﷺ, said; It's not appropriate for Prophet, to put on his armor
and prepare for war, and then take it off
until Allahعَزّوجَلّ judges between him and his enemy.
So, here Rasool Allah ﷺ is saying that
we have taken a decision, we're going to go ahead with it,
we're not going to waver, we're not going to change our minds,
we're not going to be indecisive.
If a Prophet make Shura(شورى)
and then takes a decision,
then he will go ahead with it
until Allahعَزّوجَلّ judges between him and his enemy.
I've put this armor on, I'm not going to take it out
until Allahعَزّوجَلّ judges between me and my enemy.
And this is a very important lesson for the leader.
The leader shouldn't be indecisive, the leader shouldn't change his mind every now and then,
the leader shouldn't be wavering back and forth,
according to who spoke to him last.
You make Shura(شورى), you listen to the different opinions , you deliberate,
and then you take a decision, but when you take the decision, it should be final.
Unless there's a change in information,
or the opinion was based on something that turned out to be wrong,
then a person should change.
But if the variables are the same
if the input was the same, nothing changed about it, then why change your mind.
So over here, nothing changed in this situation.
The army is still advancing, it's 3000 strong everything is the same.
And then now the Sahabah(صحابه), some of them changed their mind,
and they're asking Rasool Allah ﷺ and saying, we willing to go with what you think is right.
But it's too late now.
And the followers don't like being led by somebody who is indecisive
And that's something that, especially in War, soldiers don't like that
because a soldier is putting his life in the hands of his leader,
the Sahabahرضي الله عنهم, their lives are on the line.
And it is Rasool Allah ﷺ who's taking the decision regarding what will directly affect their lives.
So, here Rasool Allah ﷺ is giving an example to every leader, in such a situation
that if you take a decision, it needs to be final.
And there needs to be Samman Ta'ah(سمعاً طاعة), on the side of the followers, the soldiers.
So, they make a decision that they're going to go out and meet the enemy
and location was Uhud(احد), next to the mountain of Uhud(اُحَدْ).
Uhud(اُحَدْ) is a large mountain few miles outside of Madina.
The Muslim army marches
but Rasool Allah ﷺ told the Sahabah(صحابه) can any one of you, guide us through a way
that will bring us out to the enemy without them Realizing.
So, Abu Khaisamah(ابوخيثمه) said: I will.
And they travel through agricultural land
rather than the traditional routes that lead out of Madina.
And they pass through a farm owned by one of Al-Munafiqeen(منافقين), Mirbah Bin Qaidhee(مربع بن قيضي).
So, when they were walking through his farm,
obviously when an army is walking through agricultural land
it's unavoidable that there will be some damage.
So, Mirbah Bin Qaidhee(مربع بن قيضي) wanted to stop the Muslim army and he was blind.
So, he said; If you are the messenger of Allah, than I do not permit you to enter my garden,
I don't allow it to come through,
you're trespassing,
if you come through my farm or consider it trespassing you are destroying my property.
But Rasool Allah ﷺ ignores him and the Army goes forward.
So, he picks up some dirt in his hand and he said;
By Allah, if I knew I'd strike no one but you Muhammad(محمد), I'd hit you in the face with this.
This was a very disrespectful man.
So, some of the Sahabah(صحابه) attacked him, they wanted to kill him.
Because cursing Rasool Allah ﷺ is something that is punishable by death according to Islamic Sharia(شريعة),
but Rasool Allah ﷺ told them: Leave him, Don't kill him.
This sightless fellow is blind, both in heart and in his eyes.
So, they left him alone.
A lesson the benefit of the whole supersedes the benefit of the individual, in Islam.
So here, damage is done to agricultural land, which is damage done to individuals,
but it's for the benefit of the whole.
So, the whole comes before the individual.
Then the Munafiqeen(منافقين) withdrew, Abdullah Bin Obaeye(عبدالله بن ابيئ),
now the Muslim army was 1000.
Abdullah Bin Obaey(عبدالله بن ابيئ) pulls back one third of that.
So we're left with about 700 soldiers.
Now the Munafiqeen(منافقين) pulled back and the justification given by Abdullah Bin Obaeye(عبدالله بن ابيئ) was?
Muhammad(محمد), listen to the kids and he ignored my opinion.
See, because these were the young Sahabah(صحابه),
who were urging Rasool Allah ﷺ to go out, they are the ones who want to fight.
So, Abdullah Bin Obaeye(عبدالله بن ابيئ) is saying that he ignored the advice of the wise old men,
like myself, and he went by the opinion of the youngsters.
And then if there's going to be any fighting, I would come but I don't think there's going to be any fighting.
So, he leaves.
Now, Subhan Allah(سبحان الله), you can see how it is the battlefield that separates between the Momin(مؤمن) and Munafiq(منافق).
In peaceful situation, you can't know who's Munafiq(منافق) and who is Momin(مؤمن).
The Munafiq(منافق) could be anywhere.
The Munafiq(منافق) could be praying with you in the first line.
Munafiq(منافق) could be actually the one giving you Khutbah(خطبه).
Munafiq(منافق) could be the Mufti(مفتي) or the Mulla(ملا), or the Aalim(عالم), which you're asking the question,
you don't know!
who is Momin(مؤمن) and who's Munafiq(منافق).
But what separates between the believer and the hypocrite is a battlefield.
And this occurs again, and again, this is where the Munafiqeen(منافقين) show up.
So, Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
Allah will not leave the believers in that state you are in.
You know, the state they were in now, is that everybody is blended, you don't know, who is who!
مَا كَانَ اللَّهُ لِيَذَرَ الْمُؤْمِنِينَ عَلَىٰ مَا أَنْتُمْ عَلَيْهِ حَتَّىٰ يَمِيزَ الْخَبِيثَ مِنَ الطَّيِّبِ ۗ
Allah will not leave the believers in the state, in that state you are in, presently,
until he separates the evil from the good.
Allah will separate the evil from the good.
And this is how it happens.
This Aayah( آية) was revealed talking about such situations.
It's verse 179 of Al-Imran(العمران), which was revealed talking about the Battle of Uhud(اُحَدْ).
And Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
وَمَا أَصَابَكُمْ يَوْمَ الْتَقَى الْجَمْعَانِ فَبِإِذْنِ اللَّهِ وَلِيَعْلَمَ الْمُؤْمِنِينَ۝
وَلِيَعْلَمَ الَّذِينَ نَافَقُوا ۚ
وَقِيلَ لَهُمْ تَعَالَوْا قَاتِلُوا فِي سَبِيلِ اللَّهِ أَوِ ادْفَعُوا ۖ
قَالُوا لَوْ نَعْلَمُ قِتَالًا لَاتَّبَعْنَاكُمْ ۗ
هُمْ لِلْكُفْرِ يَوْمَئِذٍ أَقْرَبُ مِنْهُمْ لِلْإِيمَانِ ۚ
يَقُولُونَ بِأَفْوَاهِهِمْ مَا لَيْسَ فِي قُلُوبِهِمْ ۗ
وَاللَّهُ أَعْلَمُ بِمَا يَكْتُمُونَ۝
And what struck you on the day, the two armies met at Uhud(اُحَدْ) was by the permission of Allah,
that He might make evident the true believers
and that He might make evident those who are hypocrites.
for it was said to them come fight in the way of Allah or at least defend, they said,
if we had known there would be fighting we would have followed you.
These were the words of Abdullah Bin Obaeye(عبدالله بن ابي).
They were nearer to disbelief that day, than to faith,
saying with their mouths, what was not in their hearts
and Allah is the most knowing of what they conceal.
Actually, they're leaving because they're afraid that there's going to be fighting.
So, other way around.
Now there were two tribes who were almost going to defect.
Just like the Munafiqeen(منافقين)
and these two tribes are Bannu Salamah(بنوسلمه) and Bannu Harissa(بنوحارثه)
but Allahعَزّوجَلّ made them steadfast.
Allahعزوجل says;
إِذْ هَمَّتْ طَائِفَتَانِ مِنْكُمْ أَنْ تَفْشَلَا وَاللَّهُ وَلِيُّهُمَا ۗ
وَعَلَى اللَّهِ فَلْيَتَوَكَّلِ الْمُؤْمِنُونَ۝
When two parties among you were about to lose courage
but Allah was their ally.
And upon Allah the believers should rely.
So, this was a negative thing for these two tribes to do,
but Jaabir Ibn Abdullah(جابرابن عبدالله) said;
I wouldn't hope that this didn't happen.
Because Allah revealed the Ayah(آية) saying that He is our ally.
So, Subhan Allah(سبحان الله), it was Allah, who made them steadfast
and Allahعَزّوجَلّ revealed the verse talking about them
and saying that he's their ally and that's why, He kept them firm.
Rasool Allah ﷺ refused assistance from Mushrikeen(مشركين).
Some Jews came to help him and he said;
لَا نَسْتَعِيْنُ بِمُشْرِكْ
We don't need the help of disbelievers.
Rasool Allah ﷺ also, when the army left he turned back the under age.
For example, the ones who are under 14 or 15 years old were turned back.
Rafiah Bin Khadeej(رافع بن خديج) was turned back
because Rasool Allah ﷺ saw him,
you know they wouldn't turn them back by going and asking them how old you are.
It was by sizing them up.
Rasool Allah ﷺ would take a look at the army and whoever he would see as looking too young,
he would return him back.
So, these youngsters was trying to hide around.
So that Rasool Allah ﷺ wouldn't see them, sneaking through,
but Rasool Allah ﷺ would expose them and turn them back.
Rafiah(رافع) was one of those, who was turned away,
Abdullah Bin Umar(عبدالله بن عمر) was turned away,
Al-Bara'a Bin Aazib(ألبرآء بن عازب) was turned back
anyway and with Rafia(رافع) Rasool Allah ﷺ told him, that you're not allowed to join us.
But Rafiah(رافع) said, But Rasool Allah ﷺ I am a good Archer
and because of that he was allowed to join.
So, his friend Samorah(سموره), went to his father.
Who was actually foster father and started crying.
He said Rasool Allah ﷺ allows Rafiah(رافع) and he doesn't allow me, when I win, I can beat Rafiah(رافع) in wrestling.
So, his foster father takes him to Rasool Allah ﷺ
and told Rasool Allah ﷺ that Samora(سموره) actually defeats Rafiah(رافع) in wrestling.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ call them both
and has them wrestle in front of him.
So, they both wrestle in front of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
and Samorah(سموره) does defeat Rafiah(رافع).
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ allows him to join.
Now over here You can see the importance of training,
and how these two were allowed to join the army because they had good training.
So, because of good training, in the rules they were given an exception.
And the rules that apply to everyone didn't apply to them.
They were an exception to the rule.
Why?
Because of the good training that they had.
And this shows you the emphasis that Rasool Allah ﷺ had put on training,
one of them was a good Archer and one of them was physically fit.
The plan Rasool Allah ﷺ divided the army into three battalions,
Al-Muhajiroon(ألمهاجرون), and the standard was given to Mus'ab Ibn Umair(مصعب ابن عمير).
Al-Aos(ألاوس), and the standard was given to Usaid Bin Khuzair(أسيد بن خضير)
and Al-Khazraj(ألخزرج), the standard was handed to Al-Habbab Bin Mundhir(ألحباب بن المنزر).
Rasool Allah ﷺ had had the mountain towards his back
and Rasool Allah ﷺ when he took a look at the battlefield.
He realized that there was a potential of attack from the rear, or from the flanks,
Because there was a small hill in front of them.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ places 50 men, and 50 is a large number.
I mean, we're talking about 50, out of an army of 700.
He places 50 men, archers on top of that hill,
and he gives them very clear instructions, he said protect our backs.
If you see us being killed, don't come to our aid.
And If you see us winning, Do not join us.
And He also told them, if you see the vultures flying off with us,
Don't leave until I send you a message.
If you see us victorious over the enemy and trampling them underfoot.
Do not leave, until I send you a message.
And these two statements were narrated by Imam Ahmad(إمام احمد).
So, it's very unequivocal, very clear.
Do not come down, whether we're winning or losing, unless I tell you to do so.
So, the instructions were that they hold on to this high ground position, it's the sniper position.
Without it, the enemy could outflank the Muslims
and attack them from the side or from the rear.
So Rasool Allah ﷺ made it very clear that this is a critical position to hold on to.
Do not give it up.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ was training, his followers to have Ta'ah(طاعة), to have obedience,
he told them do not fight until I give you orders to fight.
Don't do it on your own initiative, the Ameer(امير) has to give you permission.
The enemy was trying to disunite the Muslims.
Abu Sufian(ابوسفيان) sends a message to Ansaar(أنصار), he said;
خَلُّوْ بَيْنَنَا وَ بَيْنَ اِبْنِ عَمِّنَا  فَنَنْصَرِفُ عَنْكُمْ فَلَا حَاجَة بِنَا اِلَى قِتَالِكُمْ
Al-Maqreezi(ألمقريزي) narrates that Abu Sufian(ابوسفيان) told the Ansaar(انصار).
Leave us alone to fight with our cousin.
Because we have no purpose in fighting you.
Subhaan Allah(سبحان الله), now you say this?
Isn't it Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), Who sent a letter to Al-Ansaar(ألانصار) as soon as Rasool Allah ﷺ made Hijrah(هجره) to them
threatening them that we're going to kill your men, enslave your women and take your money.
Now suddenly, you say you have no objective in fighting them.
This is but a lie, it's a trick.
And the Kuffar(كفار) did that yesterday, and they would do that today,
what they're trying to do is split the Muslims into bite size,
so that they could eat them one by one.
And as the saying goes,
I was eaten, the day the white bull was eaten.
So, it is only to defeat one portion at a time.
And if the Ansaar(انصار) would have allowed that to happen, they would have been next,
just like we see today
the claim is that we're just fighting the terrorists,
but the rest of the Muslims are fine, they're peaceful, we don't have a problem with them.
That's just a strategy for the day.
But after the so called terrorists are defeated,
they would move on to the next stage and the rest of the Ummah(امة).
We've been hearing this thing again and again.
This just Palestine now and it's just Iraq now.
And tomorrow we're going to see some other Muslim countries invaded,
and their wealth is plundered,
if the Muslims don't stand up and unite.
The people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) tried again to disunite the Muslims by sending Abu Aamir Al-Fasiq(ابوعامرالفاسق).
Abu Aamir(ابوعامر) was one of Al-Aos(اَلاَوس)
and he was so loved by them and his he was such a righteous man,
a religious man, he was called Abu Aamir Ar-Rahib(ابوعامر الراهب), the priest, the monk.
That's the name, his people gave him because he was such a nice person who would worship Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
He refused to become Muslim and he joined the army of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ)
and he has been with him for some time.
He left Madina when Islam entered it.
And when he came out to the army of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
He said;
I will go and convince my people not to fight with Muhammadﷺ,
and he was confident that he could do so because they loved him so much they wouldn't turn him down.
But when he went to meet them, they started cursing him.
So, he said some evil has befallen my people after I left.
It's not evil, it's Islam that changed them.
So, the second attempt to disunite the Ummah(امة) failed.
We'll stop here In sha Allah ho Ta'ala(اِنْ شاء الله تعالى).
صَلَّى الله عَلى سَيَّدِنَا محمد وَعَلى اَلِهِ وَ صَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًا كَثِيْرًا
وَالسلام عليكم ورحمة الله وبركاته